NumPy includes a powerful data structure known as an array. 
A NumPy array is a special type of list. It’s a data structure that organizes 
multiple items. Each item can be of any type (strings, numbers, or even other arrays).

Arrays are most powerful when they are used to store numbers. 
This is because arrays give us special ways of performing mathematical 
operations that are both simpler to write and more efficient computationally. 
We’ll get more into this later.

A NumPy array looks a lot like a Python list:

my_array = np.array([1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6])
We can transform a regular list into a NumPy array by using np.array() 
and saving the value to a new variable:

my_list = [1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6]
my_array = np.array(my_list)

We’re able to transform CSV (comma-separated values) 
files into arrays using the np.genfromtxt() function:

Consider the following CSV, sample.csv,

34,9,12,11,7
We can import this into a NumPy array using the following code:

csv_array = np.genfromtxt('sample.csv', delimiter=',')
Note that in this case, our file sample.csv has values separated by commas, so we use delimiter=',', but sometimes you’ll find files with other delimiters, the most common being tabs or colons.

Once imported, this CSV will create the array

>>> csv_array

Let’s compare how to add a number to each value in a python list versus a NumPy array:

# With a list
l = [1, 2, 3, 4, 5]
l_plus_3 = []
for i in range(len(l)):
    l_plus_3.append(l[i] + 3)

# With an array
a = np.array(l)
a_plus_3 = a + 3

As we can see, if we were to add 3 to every number in a list, we would have to use a for loop or a list comprehension. With an array, we can just add 3. The same is true for subtraction, multiplication, and division.
array([34, 9, 12, 11, 7])


np.sqrt(a)
a**2

n the previous exercises we had stored the student’s test scores in separate one-dimensional arrays for each test:

test_1 = np.array([92, 94, 88, 91, 87])
test_2 = np.array([79, 100, 86, 93, 91])
test_3 = np.array([87, 85, 72, 90, 92])
But we could have also stored all of this data in a single, two-dimensional array:

np.array([[92, 94, 88, 91, 87], 
          [79, 100, 86, 93, 91],
          [87, 85, 72, 90, 92]])
Here, each row represents a test, and each column represents a student. 
This allows us to store all of our data in a single array without losing any of its organization.

As we mentioned, a two-dimensional array is a list of lists where 
each list has the same number of elements. Here are some examples 
that are not two-dimensional arrays.

This code will run but it will not create a two-dimensional 
array because the lists have different numbers of elements:

np.array([[29, 49,  6], 
          [77,  1]])

a = np.array([5, 2, 7, 0, 11])
If we wanted to select the first element in this array, we would call:

>>> a[0]
5 
In typical Python fashion, the indices for an array start at 0. 
This is known as zero-indexed numbering.
 In the array above, 5 is known as the zeroth element, a[0]. 
It follows that 2 is the first element, a[1].


If we wanted to select multiple elements in the array, we can define a range, 
such as a[1:3], which will select all the elements from a[1] to a[3], 
including a[1] but excluding a[3].

>>> a[1:3]
array([2, 7])
Similarly, if we wanted to select all elements before a[3] we would use:

>>> a[:3]
array([5, 2, 7])
We can also use negative indices to select multiple elements. 
Let’s say we want to select the last 3 elements in an array:

>>> a[-3:]
array([7, 0, 11])
This code will not run because the [] for the outer lists are missing:

np.array([68, 16, 73],
         [61, 79, 30])

Our students’ test scores are now stored in the 2-d array student_scores. 
The first row stores the scores of the first test, the second row the second test, 
and the third row the third test, as shown in the following table:

Tanya	Manual	Adwoa	Jeremy	Cody
test_1	92	94	88	91	87
test_2	79	100	86	93	91
test_3	87	85	72	90	92

Tanya wants to know how well she did on third test. 
Select her score from the array and save it to tanya_test_3.
tanya_test_3=student_scores[2,0]

You have a parent teacher conference with Cody’s parents coming up and would like to have all of his test scores handy.

Select all of Cody’s test scores and save them to a new array cody_test_scores.
cody_test_scores=student_scores[:,4]


Another useful thing that arrays can do is perform element-wise logical operations. 
For instance, suppose we want to know how many elements in an array are greater than 5. 
We can easily write some code that checks to see whether this statement evaluates to True for each item in the array, without having to use a for loop :

>>> a = np.array([10, 2, 2, 4, 5, 3, 9, 8, 9, 7])
>>> a > 5
array([True, False, False, False, False, False, True, True, True, True], dtype=bool)


We can then use logical operators to evaluate and select items based on certain criteria. To select all elements from the previous array that are greater than 5, we’d write the following:

>>> a[a > 5]
array([10, 9, 8, 9, 7])
We can also combine logical statements to further specify our criteria. To do so, we place each statement in parentheses and use boolean operators like & (and) and | (or).

In our example, we can use combined statements to find the elements that are greater than five or less than two:

>>> a[(a > 5) | (a < 2)]
array([10, 9, 8, 9, 7])

1.
You are working on a team of climate scientists and one of your roles is to
 take the weekly temperature data and input into NumPy arrays for later analysis. 
The sensor records the temperature 4 times a day, at 0:00, 6:00, 12:00, and 18:00. 
You are given last weeks data (Monday through Friday) and asked to create a NumPy array.

Get started by importing the numpy package.


2.
Create an array temperatures by importing the data in the CSV temperature_data.csv

(CSV based on data from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration)

3.
Inspect the data by printing it to the terminal.

The columns are the times, starting at 0:00, and the rows are days, 
starting on Monday, and the values are the recorded temperatures at that time 
on those days.

4.
One of the researchers noticed that the sensor had been incorrectly zeroed 
and all of the recorded temperatures are 3.0 degrees too cold.

Adjust the array so that the temperature readings are accurate and save them to 
temperatures_fixed.

5.
Another researcher asked you for the temperature values from Monday. 
Save them to a new array, monday_temperatures.

6.
“Hmmm, interesting” the researcher mumbles, “can you also give me the 6:00 AM data 
for Thursday and Friday?”

Save this data to a new array thursday_friday_morning.

7.
Finally, the persistent researcher now wants all the high and low temperatures 
over the week.

Select all temperatures that are under 50 degrees or over 60 degrees and save 
them to a new array temperature_extremes.


temperatures=[[ 43.6  45.1  58.8  53. ]
 [ 47.   44.5  58.3  52.6]
 [ 46.7  44.2  57.9  52.2]
 [ 46.5  44.1  57.6  51.9]
 [ 46.2  43.9  57.2  51.5]]





INTRODUCTION TO STATISTICS WITH NUMPY
Betty's Bakery
Betty has always used her grandmother’s recipe book to make cookies, cakes, pancakes, and bread for her friends and family. She’s getting ready to open a business and will need to start buying all of her milk, eggs, sugar, flour, and butter in bulk.

Help Betty figure out how much she needs to buy using NumPy arrays describing her recipes.

If you get stuck during this project or would like to see an experienced developer work through it, click “Get Help“ to see a project walkthrough video.

Tasks
1/10Complete
Mark the tasks as complete by checking them off
Reading Recipes
1.
Start by importing NumPy as np.

2.
All of Betty’s recipes call for milk, eggs, sugar, flour, and butter. For example, her cupcake recipe calls for:

|Flour|Sugar|Eggs|Milk|Butter| |-|-|-|-| |2 cups|0.75 cups|2 eggs|1 cups|0.5 cups|

Create a NumPy array that represents this data. Each element should be a number (i.e., 2 for “2 cups”). Save this array as cupcakes.

3.
Betty’s assistant has compiled all of her recipes into a csv (comma-separated variable) file called recipes.csv. Load this file into a variable called recipes.

4.
Display recipes using print.

Each row represents a different recipe. Each column represents a different ingredient.

|Recipe|Cups of Flour|Cups of Sugar|Eggs|Cups of Milk|Cups of Butter| |-|-|-|-|-| |Cupcakes|…|…|…|…|…| |Pancake|…|…|…|…|…| |Cookie|…|…|…|…|…| |Bread|…|…|…|…|…|

5.
The 3rd column represents the number of eggs that each recipe needs.

Select all elements from the 3rd column and save them to the variable eggs.

6.
Which recipes require exactly 1 egg? Use a logical statement to get True or False for each value of eggs.

7.
Betty is going to make 2 batches of cupcakes (1st row) and 1 batch of cookies (3rd row).

You already have a variable for cupcakes. Create a variable for cookies with the data from the 3rd row.

8.
Get the number of ingredients for a double batch of cupcakes by using multiplication on cupcakes. Save your new variable to double_batch.

9.
Create a new variable called grocery_list by adding cookies and double_batch.

10.
Click here for a video walkthrough from our experts to help you check your work!

recipes=[[ 2.     0.75   2.     1.     0.5  ]
 [ 1.     0.125  1.     1.     0.125]
 [ 2.75   1.5    1.     0.     1.   ]
 [ 4.     0.5    2.     2.     0.5  ]]


import numpy as np
cupcakes= np.array([2,0.75,2,1,0.5])
recipes=np.genfromtxt('recipes.csv',delimiter=',')
print(recipes)
eggs=recipes[:,2]
print(eggs)
print(eggs==1)
cookies=recipes[2,:]
print(cookies)
double_batch=cupcakes*2
print(double_batch)
grocery_list=cookies+double_batch
   

https://s3.amazonaws.com/codecademy-content/courses/numpy/intro-stats-numpy.html

stats : 
Mean and Logical Operations
We can also use np.mean to calculate the percent of array elements that have a certain property.

As we know, a logical operator will evaluate each item in an array to see if it matches the specified condition. 
If the item matches the given condition, the item will evaluate as True and equal 1. If it does not match, it will be False and equal 0.

When np.mean calculates a logical statement, the resulting mean value will be equivalent 
to the total number of True items divided by the total array length.

In our produce survey example, we can use this calculation to find out the percentage 
of people who bought more than 8 pounds of produce each week:

>>> np.mean(survey_array > 8)
0.2
The logical statement survey_array > 8 evaluates which survey answers were greater than 8, and assigns them a value of 1. np.
mean adds all of the 1s up and divides them by the length of survey_array. The resulting output tells us that 
20% of responders purchased more than 8 pounds of produce.




Calculating the Mean of 2D Arrays
If we have a two-dimensional array, np.mean can calculate the means of the larger array as well as the interior values.

Let’s imagine a game of ring toss at a carnival. In this game, you have three different chances to get all three rings onto a stick. In our ring_toss array, each interior array (the arrays within the larger array) is one try, and each number is one ring toss. 1 represents a successful toss, 0 represents a fail.

First, we can use np.mean to find the mean across all the arrays:

>>> ring_toss = np.array([[1, 0, 0], 
                          [0, 0, 1], 
                          [1, 0, 1]])
>>> np.mean(ring_toss)
0.44444444444444442
To find the means of each interior array, we specify axis 1 (the “rows”):

>>> np.mean(ring_toss, axis=1)
array([ 0.33333333,  0.33333333,  0.66666667])
To find the means of each index position (i.e, mean of all 1st tosses, mean of all 2nd tosses, …), we specify axis 0 (the “columns”):

>>> np.mean(ring_toss, axis=0)
array([ 0.66666667,  0.        ,  0.66666667])


Outliers
As we can see, the mean is a helpful way to quickly understand different parts of our data. However, the mean is highly influenced by the specific values in our data set. What happens when one of those values is significantly different from the rest?

Values that don’t fit within the majority of a dataset are known as outliers. It’s important to identify outliers because if they go unnoticed, they can skew our data and lead to error in our analysis (like determining the mean). They can also be useful in pointing out errors in our data collection.

When we’re able to identify outliers, we can then determine if they were due to an error in sample collection or whether or not they represent a significant but real deviation from the mean.

Suppose we want to determine the average height for 3rd graders. We measure several students at the local school, but accidentally measure one student in centimeters rather than in inches. If we’re not paying attention, our dataset could end up looking like this:

[50, 50, 51, 49, 48, 127]
In this case, 127 would be an outlier.

Some outliers aren’t the result of a mistake. For instance, suppose that one of our 3rd graders had skipped a grade and was actually a year younger than everyone else in the class:

[50, 50, 51, 49, 48, 45]
She might be significantly shorter at 45”, but her height would still be an outlier.

Suppose that another student was just unusually tall for his age:

[50, 50, 51, 49, 48, 58.5]
His height of 58.5” would also be an outlier.

In a dataset, the median value can provide an important comparison to the mean.
 Unlike a mean, the median is not affected by outliers.
 This becomes important in skewed datasets, datasets whose values are not distributed evenly.


Percentiles, Part I
As we know, the median is the middle of a dataset: it is the number for which 50% of the samples are below, and 50% of the samples are above. But what if we wanted to find a point at which 40% of the samples are below, and 60% of the samples are above?

This type of point is called a percentile. The Nth percentile is defined as the point N% of samples lie below it. So the point where 40% of samples are below is called the 40th percentile. Percentiles are useful measurements because they can tell us where a particular value is situated within the greater dataset.

Let’s look at the following array:

d = [1, 2, 3, 4, 4, 4, 6, 6, 7, 8, 8]
There are 11 numbers in the dataset. The 40th percentile will have 40% of the 10 remaining numbers below it (40% of 10 is 4) and 60% of the numbers above it (60% of 10 is 6). So in this example, the 40th percentile is 4.

percentile

In NumPy, we can calculate percentiles using the function np.percentile, which takes two arguments: the array and the percentile to calculate.

Here’s how we would use NumPy to calculate the 40th percentile of array d:

>>> d = np.array([1, 2, 3, 4, 4, 4, 6, 6, 7,  8, 8])
>>> np.percentile(d, 40)
4.00


The 25th percentile is called the first quartile
The 50th percentile is called the median
The 75th percentile is called the third quartile

The minimum, first quartile, median, third quartile, and maximum of a dataset are called a five-number summary. This set of numbers is a great thing to compute when we get a new dataset.

The difference between the first and third quartile is a value called the interquartile range. For example, say we have the following array:

d = [1, 2, 3, 4, 4, 4, 6, 6, 7, 8, 8]
We can calculate the 25th and 75th percentiles using np.percentile:

np.percentile(d, 25)
>>> 3.5
np.percentile(d, 75)
>>> 6.5
Then to find the interquartile range, we subtract the value of the 25th percentile from the value of the 75th:

6.5 - 3.5 = 3
50% of the dataset will lie within the interquartile range. 
The interquartile range gives us an idea of how spread out our data is. 
The smaller the interquartile range value, the less variance in our dataset. 
The greater the value, the larger the variance.

While the mean and median can tell us about the center of our data, 
they do not reflect the range of the data. That’s where standard deviation comes in.

Similar to the interquartile range, 
the standard deviation tells us the spread of the data. 
The larger the standard deviation, the more spread out our data is from the center. 
The smaller the standard deviation, the more the data is clustered around the mean.


CrunchieMunchies
You work in marketing for a food company YummyCorps, which is developing a new kind of tasty, wholesome cereal called CrunchieMunchies. You want to demonstrate to consumers how healthy your cereal is in comparison to other leading brands, so you’ve dug up nutritional data on several different competitors.

Your task is to use NumPy statistical calculations to analyze this data and prove that your CrunchieMunchies cereal is the healthiest choice for consumers.

If you get stuck during this project or would like to see an experienced developer work through it, click “Get Help“ to see a project walkthrough video.

Tasks
9/9Complete
Mark the tasks as complete by checking them off
PROJECT STEPS
1.
First, import numpy.

2.
Look over the cereal.csv file. This file contains the reported calorie amounts for different cereal brands. Load the data from the file and save it as calorie_stats.

To learn more about reading data from a CSV using NumPy, read this documentation page.

3.
There are 60 calories per serving of CrunchieMunchies. How much higher is the average calorie count of your competition?

Save the answer to the variable average_calories and print the variable to the terminal to see the answer.

4.
Does the average calorie count adequately reflect the distribution of the dataset? Let’s sort the data and see.

Sort the data and save the result to the variable calorie_stats_sorted. Print the sorted data to the terminal.

5.
Do you see what I’m seeing? Looks like the majority of the cereals are higher than the mean. Let’s see if the median is a better representative of the dataset.

Calculate the median of the dataset and save your answer to median_calories. Print the median so you can see how it compares to the mean.

6.
While the median demonstrates that at least half of our values are over 100 calories, it would be more impressive to show that a significant portion of the competition has a higher calorie count that CrunchieMunchies.

Calculate different percentiles and print them to the terminal until you find the lowest percentile that is greater than 60 calories. Save this value to the variable nth_percentile.

7.
While the percentile shows us that the majority of the competition has a much higher calorie count, it’s an awkward concept to use in marketing materials.

Instead, let’s calculate the percentage of cereals that have more than 60 calories per serving. Save your answer to the variable more_calories and print it to the terminal.

We can find percentages when we use logical operators in combination with np.mean. So, to find the percentage of values in a dataset with a value greater than x, we’d write:

percentage = np.mean(dataset > x)
8.
Wow! That’s a really high percentage. That’s going to be very useful when we promote CrunchieMunchies. But one question is, how much variation exists in the dataset? Can we make the generalization that most cereals have around 100 calories or is the spread even greater?

Calculate the amount of variation by finding the standard deviation. Save your answer to calorie_std and print to the terminal. How can we incorporate this value into our analysis?

import codecademylib
import numpy as np
calorie_stats=np.genfromtxt('cereal.csv',delimiter=',')
average_calories=np.mean(calorie_stats)
print(calorie_stats)
print(average_calories)
calorie_stats_sorted=np.sort(calorie_stats)

print(calorie_stats_sorted)
median_calories=np.median(calorie_stats)

print(median_calories)
first_quarter= np.percentile(calorie_stats,25)
print(first_quarter)
sec_quarter= np.percentile(calorie_stats,15)
print(sec_quarter)
third_quarter=np.percentile(calorie_stats,5)
print(third_quarter)
fourth_quarter=np.percentile(calorie_stats,4)
print(fourth_quarter)
nth_percentile=fourth_quarter
more_calories=np.mean(calorie_stats>60)
print(more_calories)

calorie_std=np.std(calorie_stats)
print(calorie_std)



Supervised vs. Unsupervised
Introduction to the two main classes of algorithms in Machine Learning — Supervised Learning & Unsupervised Learning.

As humans, we have many different ways we learn things. The way you learned calculus, for example, is probably not the same way you learned to stack blocks. The way you learned the alphabet is probably wildly different from the way you learned how to tell if objects are approaching you or going away from you. The latter you might not even realize you learned at all!

Similarly, when we think about making programs that can learn, we have to think about these programs learning in different ways. Two main ways that we can approach machine learning are Supervised Learning and Unsupervised Learning. Both are useful for different situations or kinds of data available.

Supervised Learning
Let’s imagine you’re first learning about different genres in music. Your music teacher plays you an indie rock song and says “This is an indie rock song”. Then, they play you a K-pop song and tell you “This is a K-pop song”. Then, they play you a techno track and say “This is techno”. You go through many examples of these genres.

The next time you’re listening to the radio, and you hear techno, you may think “This is similar to the 5 techno tracks I heard in class today. This must be techno!”

Even though the teacher didn’t tell you about this techno track, she gave you enough examples of songs that were techno, so you could recognize more examples of it.

When we explicitly tell a program what we expect the output to be, and let it learn the rules that produce expected outputs from given inputs, we are performing supervised learning.

Supervised Learning GIF


A common example of this is image classification. Often, we want to build systems that will be able to describe a picture. To do this, we normally show a program thousands of examples of pictures, with labels that describe them. During this process, the program adjusts its internal parameters. Then, when we show it a new example of a photo with an unknown description, it should be able to produce a reasonable description of the photo.

When you complete a Captcha and identify the images that have cars, you’re labeling images! A supervised machine learning algorithm can now use those pictures that you’ve tagged to make it’s car-image predictor more accurate.

Unsupervised Learning
Let’s say you are an alien who has been observing the meals people eat. You’ve embedded yourself into the body of an employee at a typical tech startup, and you see people eating breakfasts, lunches, and snacks. Over the course of a couple weeks, you surmise that for breakfast people mostly eat foods like:

Cereals
Bagels
Granola bars
Lunch is usually a combination of:

Some sort of vegetable
Some sort of protein
Some sort of grain
Snacks are usually a piece of fruit or a handful of nuts. No one explicitly told you what kinds of foods go with each meal, but you learned from natural observation and put the patterns together. In unsupervised learning, we don’t tell the program anything about what we expect the output to be. The program itself analyzes the data it encounters and tries to pick out patterns and group the data in meaningful ways.

Unsupervised Learning


An example of this includes clustering to create segments in a business’s user population. In this case, an unsupervised learning algorithm would probably create groups (or clusters) based on parameters that a human may not even consider.

Summary
We have gone over the difference between supervised and unsupervised learning:

Supervised Learning: data is labeled and the program learns to predict the output from the input data
Unsupervised Learning: data is unlabeled and the program learns to recognize the inherent structure in the input data



cheatsheet:
Scikit-learn is a library in Python that provides many unsupervised and supervised learning algorithms. It’s built upon some of the technology you might already be familiar with, like NumPy, pandas, and Matplotlib!

As you build robust Machine Learning programs, it’s helpful to have all the sklearn commands all in one place in case you forget.

Linear Regression
Import and create the model:

from sklearn.linear_model import LinearRegression

your_model = LinearRegression()
Fit:

your_model.fit(x_training_data, y_training_data)
.coef_: contains the coefficients
.intercept_: contains the intercept
Predict:

predictions = your_model.predict(your_x_data)
.score(): returns the coefficient of determination R²
Naive Bayes
Import and create the model:

from sklearn.naive_bayes import MultinomialNB

your_model = MultinomialNB()
Fit:

your_model.fit(x_training_data, y_training_data)
Predict:

# Returns a list of predicted classes - one prediction for every data point
predictions = your_model.predict(your_x_data)

# For every data point, returns a list of probabilities of each class
probabilities = your_model.predict_proba(your_x_data)
K-Nearest Neighbors
Import and create the model:

from sklearn.neigbors import KNeighborsClassifier

your_model = KNeighborsClassifier()
Fit:

your_model.fit(x_training_data, y_training_data)
Predict:

# Returns a list of predicted classes - one prediction for every data point
predictions = your_model.predict(your_x_data)

# For every data point, returns a list of probabilities of each class
probabilities = your_model.predict_proba(your_x_data)
K-Means
Import and create the model:

from sklearn.cluster import KMeans

your_model = KMeans(n_clusters=4, init='random')
n_clusters: number of clusters to form and number of centroids to generate
init: method for initialization
k-means++: K-Means++ [default]
random: K-Means
random_state: the seed used by the random number generator [optional]
Fit:

your_model.fit(x_training_data)
Predict:

predictions = your_model.predict(your_x_data)
Validating the Model
Import and print accuracy, recall, precision, and F1 score:

from sklearn.metrics import accuracy_score, recall_score, precision_score, f1_score

print(accuracy_score(true_labels, guesses))
print(recall_score(true_labels, guesses))
print(precision_score(true_labels, guesses))
print(f1_score(true_labels, guesses))
Import and print the confusion matrix:

from sklearn.metrics import confusion_matrix

print(confusion_matrix(true_labels, guesses))
Training Sets and Test Sets
from sklearn.model_selection import train_test_split

x_train, x_test, y_train, y_test = train_test_split(x, y, train_size=0.8, test_size=0.2)
train_size: the proportion of the dataset to include in the train split
test_size: the proportion of the dataset to include in the test split
random_state: the seed used by the random number generator [optional]



Euclidean Distance
Manhattan Distance
Hamming Distance
Before diving into the distance formulas, it is first important to consider how to represent points in your code.

In this exercise, we will use a list, where each item in the list represents a dimension of the point. For example, the point (5, 8) could be represented in Python like this:

pt1 = [5, 8]
Points aren’t limited to just two dimensions. For example, a five-dimensional point could be represented as [4, 8, 15, 16, 23].

Ultimately, we want to find the distance between two points. We’ll be writing functions that look like this:

distance([1, 2, 3], [5, 8, 9])
Note that we can only find the difference between two points if they have the same number of dimensions!


Euclidean Distance
Euclidean Distance is the most commonly used distance formula. To find the Euclidean distance between two points, we first calculate the squared distance between each dimension. If we add up all of these squared differences and take the square root, we’ve computed the Euclidean distance.

Let’s take a look at the equation that represents what we just learned:

\sqrt{(a_1-b_1)^2+(a_2-b_2)^2+\ldots+(a_n - b_n)^2} 

​	 
The image below shows a visual of Euclidean distance being calculated:

The Euclidean distance between two points.

d = \sqrt{(a_1-b_1)^2+(a_2-b_2)^2}d= 



distance=0
  sum=0
  if len(pt1)==len(pt2):
    for i in range (len(pt1)):
      sum+= (pt1[i]-pt2[i])**2
    distance= sqrt(sum)


Manhattan Distance
Manhattan Distance is extremely similar to Euclidean distance. Rather than summing the squared difference between each dimension, we instead sum the absolute value of the difference between each dimension. It’s called Manhattan distance because it’s similar to how you might navigate when walking city blocks. If you’ve ever wondered “how many blocks will it take me to get from point A to point B”, you’ve computed the Manhattan distance.

The equation is shown below:

|a1 - b1| + |a2 - b2 | + ..... + | an - bn |

def euclidean_distance(pt1, pt2):
  distance = 0
  for i in range(len(pt1)):
    distance += (pt1[i] - pt2[i]) ** 2
  return distance ** 0.5

def manhattan_distance(pt1, pt2):
  distance = 0
  for i in range(len(pt1)):
    distance += abs(pt1[i] - pt2[i])
  return distance

Hamming Distance
Hamming Distance is another slightly different variation on the distance formula. 
Instead of finding the difference of each dimension, Hamming distance only cares about 
whether the dimensions are exactly equal. When finding the Hamming distance between two points, 
add one for every dimension that has different values.

Hamming distance is used in spell checking algorithms. For example, the Hamming distance 
between the word “there” and the typo “thete” is one. Each letter is a dimension, and each 
dimension has the same value except for one. 


def hamming_distance(pt1,pt2):
  distance=0
  for i in range(len(pt1)):
    if(pt1[i]!=pt2[i]):
      distance+=1
  return distance

Python’s SciPy library:

Euclidean Distance .euclidean()
Manhattan Distance .cityblock()
Hamming Distance .hamming()


Regression vs. Classification
Learn about the two types of Supervised Learning algorithms.

Machine Learning is a set of many different techniques that are each suited to answering different types of questions.

We have previously divided algorithms into two groups — Supervised Learning vs Unsupervised Learning. Supervised learning algorithms use labeled data as input while unsupervised learning algorithms use unlabeled data. However, we can further distinguish machine learning algorithms by the output they produce. In terms of output, two main types of machine learning models exist: those for regression and those for classification.

Regression
Regression is used to predict outputs that are continuous. The outputs are quantities that can be flexibly determined based on the inputs of the model rather than being confined to a set of possible labels.

For example:

Predict the height of a potted plant from the amount of rainfall
Predict salary based on someone’s age and availability of high-speed internet
Predict a car’s MPG (miles per gallon) based on size and model year
Regression GIF


Linear regression is the most popular regression algorithm. It is often underrated because of its relative simplicity. In a business setting, it could be used to predict the likelihood that a customer will churn or the revenue a customer will generate. More complex models may fit this data better, at the cost of losing simplicity.

Classification
Classification is used to predict a discrete label. The outputs fall under a finite set of possible outcomes. Many situations have only two possible outcomes. This is called binary classification (True/False, 0 or 1, Hotdog / not Hotdog).

For example:

Predict whether an email is spam or not
Predict whether it will rain or not
Predict whether a user is a power user or a casual user
Multi-label classification is when there are multiple possible outcomes. It is useful for customer segmentation, image categorization, and sentiment analysis for understanding text. To perform these classifications, we use models like Naive Bayes, K-Nearest Neighbors, and SVMs.

Classification GIF


Choosing a model is a critical step in the Machine Learning process. It is important that the model fits the question at hand. When you choose the right model, you are already one step closer to getting meaningful and interesting results.


The Machine Learning Process
Learn the general structure of how to approach Machine Learning problems in a methodical way.

The Process
When people think of Machine Learning, they often think of a program that is taking in data and spitting out predictions and insights. The process of performing Machine Learning often requires many more steps before and after the predictive analytics.

We try to think of the Machine Learning process as:

Formulating a Question
Finding and Understanding the Data
Cleaning the Data and Feature Engineering
Choosing a Model
Tuning and Evaluating
Using the Model and Presenting Results
1. Formulating a Question
What is it that we want to find out? How will we reach the success criteria that we set?

Let’s say we are performing machine learning for a high-traffic fast-casual restaurant chain, and our goal is to improve the customer experience. We can serve this goal in many ways. When we’re thinking about creating a model, we have to narrow down to one measurable, specific task. For example, we might say we want to predict the wait times for customers’ food orders within 2 minutes, so that we can give them an accurate time estimate.

2. Finding and Understanding the Data
Arguably the largest chunk of time in any machine learning process is finding the relevant data to help answer your question, and getting it into the format necessary for performing predictive analysis.

We know that for supervised learning, we need labeled datasets, or datasets that have clear labels of what their ground truth is. For an example like the restaurant wait time, this would mean we would need many examples of past orders, tagged with how long the wait time was. Maybe the restaurant already tracks this data, but we might need to augment the data collection with a timer that starts when the customer orders, stops when the customer receives their food, and records that information.

Creating this system of recording data, as well as gathering enough data to be able to train our model will take time.

Once you have your data, you want to understand it so that you will know what model to apply and what the outputs will mean. First, you will want to examine the summary statistics:

Calculate means and medians to understand the distribution
Calculate percentiles
Find correlations that indicate relationships
You may also want to visualize the data, perhaps using box plots to identify outliers, histograms to show the basic structure of the data, and scatter plots to examine relationships between variables.

Let’s say we’re examining the existing distribution of wait times. We see that the overall average is 6.25 minutes per order. But we also produce this histogram:

histogram of wait times

We might glean from this that there are two main groups of orders. One group seems to cluster around 4 minutes, while another, smaller, group seems to cluster around 11 mins. We could use this to modify our question and build a model that will classify whether or not an order will be in this “short” timeframe, or in the “long” timeframe. Is it dependent on the food that it ordered? The time of day of the order?

Perhaps we just become aware of the bimodality of our data. If our model consistently predicts a wait time of around 6 or 7 minutes, then we are not taking into account the true structure of our data.

3. Cleaning the Data and Feature Engineering
Real data is messy! Data may have errors. Some columns may be empty. The features we’re interested in might require string manipulation to extract. Cleaning the data refers to the process by which we address missing values and outliers, among other things that may affect our insights.

We may see that we have a group of orders that took over 20 minutes, due to an emergency in the kitchen one afternoon. This is pushing our average wait time up, and may skew our predictions. If we want to model the more general functioning of the restaurant, we may want to remove these values.

Feature Engineering refers to the process by which we choose the important features (or columns) to look at, and make the appropriate transformations to prepare our data for our model.

We might try:

Normalizing or standardizing the data
Augmenting the data by adding new columns
Removing unnecessary columns
After we test our model on the data we have, we might go back and reengineer features to see if we get a better result.

4. Choosing a Model
Once we understand our dataset and know the problem we are trying to solve, we can begin to choose a model that will help us tackle our problem.

If we are attempting to find a continuous output, like predicting the number of minutes someone should wait for their order, we would use a regression algorithm.

If we are attempting to classify an input, like determining if an order will take under 5 minutes or over 10 mins, then we would use a classification algorithm.

The different classification and regression algorithms work better on different types of datasets. We use different models on categorical and numerical data, and different models on datasets with many features and datasets with few features. Our models also have different levels of interpretability — how easy is it for us to see what these results mean and what led to them? When we teach the models, we will discuss the tradeoffs of using each one.

5. Tuning and Evaluating
We often want to set a metric of success, so that we know the model we’ve chosen is good enough. Are we looking for accuracy? Precision? Some combination of the two? We discuss this in our lesson on Precision and Accuracy.

Each model has a variety of parameters that change how it makes decisions. We can adjust these and compare the chosen evaluation metrics of the different variants to find the most accurate model.

For example, let’s say we’re using a K-Nearest Neighbors regression algorithm to solve the wait time prediction problem. This algorithm uses a parameter k, which you will learn about in the KNN lesson. We can adjust k to get different results.

Is it ideal to compare against 3 nearest neighbors? 10? 1? We can try many different values of k and see which one gives us the highest level of accuracy:

line graph of accuracy

From this analysis, we would set our k to be 26, which got the highest level of accuracy.

6. Using the Model and Presenting Results
When you achieve the level of accuracy you want on your training set, you can use the model on the data you actually care about analyzing.

For our example, we can now start inputting new orders. The input could be an order, with features like:

the type of item ordered
the quantity
the time of day
the number of employees working
The output would be how long the order is expected to take. This information could be displayed to users.

An important step is being able to convey what you’ve learned and created, so that people can use it in the future.

Sometimes you learn more about your data by looking at the model. For example, using Multiple Learning Regression can give you insights into the importance of each feature. We can create a feature importance graph to visualize this for those unfamiliar with our model:

feature importance

Your Process
The process we have outlined is a fairly standard process for performing machine learning. As you get experience going through this process on your own, with your own problems, you will start to form your own process. The steps may not be linear! As you clean your data, you may uncover a better question to ask. As you tune your model, you may realize you need more data, and go back to the collection step.

The important part is to stay curious, and to keep iterating until you find a model that works the best!